<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a minister to a person of quality shewing some reasons for his nonconformity.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11825122</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11825122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27031)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 806:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a minister to a person of quality shewing some reasons for his nonconformity.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: A.B.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49675:1"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> from a <hi>MINISTER</hi> to a Perſon of Quality, ſhewing ſome Reaſons for his Non-conformity.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU were pleaſed to require of me the reaſon of my Non-conformity; in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with your command, I promiſed to give you ſome account of it, but not the tythe which might be ſaid in the cauſe; and therefore ſhall not put the whole matter and iſſue, upon what I have here ſuddenly committed to Paper, but only to ſatisfie you, that I have ſomewhat of apology for my not conforming, and that I ſeem (at leaſt to my ſelf) not wilful and fanatical, but rational and conſcientious in refuſing.</p>
            <p>Three grand declarations are required to be made by all thoſe who will conform: The firſt <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Book of Common-Prayer;</hi> the ſecond concerning <hi>taking up arms againſt the King;</hi> the third concerning the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant.</hi> Now with reference to all theſe (eſpecially the firſt and laſt) I have had hitherto inſuperable objections againſt the making any ſuch Declaration.</p>
            <p>The firſt Declaration concerning the Book of Common-Prayer is to be made in theſe very words, <hi>viz. I</hi> A. B. <hi>do declare my unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by the Book, intituled, The Book of Common-Prayer, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other rites and ceremonies of the Church, according to the uſe of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>together with the Pſalter or Pſalms of</hi> David, <hi>pointed as they are to be ſung or ſaid in Churches, and the form and manner of making, ordaining, and conſecrating of Biſhops, Priests and Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> Here is required <hi>aſſent and conſent,</hi> yea <hi>unfeigned aſſent and conſent;</hi> and not only to <hi>all in general,</hi> but to <hi>every thing in particular contained in and preſcribed by the Book of Common-Prayer,</hi> even whatſoever is there printed, and ſet down from the very beginning of it to the very end of the ſame. Surely words could not be deviſed by all the wit of man more comprehenſive, and more ſignificant, to teſtifie our higheſt juſtification and commendation of every point and ſyllable, of every rite and ceremony, of every matter and thing contained in the whole Book, and in every page and line of it. A man might well think that this Book of Common-Prayer dropped immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately out of Heaven, and that it is nothing elſe but a continued Oracle from firſt to laſt. I think here is as much fully to be declared concerning the Book of Common-Prayer, as poſſibly can be concerning the Book of God, the Bible it ſelf. Yea I queſtion whether many a ſober man would not ſcruple to declare ſo much concerning any copy of the Bible now extant in the world in any language whatſoever, even the Originals themſelves not excepted, which by tranſcribing may have their faults, and therefore, every thing contained in them not to be unfeignedly aſſented and conſented unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> We Proteſtants proteſt vehemently againſt the Popes Infallibility, and with the ſame reaſon againſt the Infallibility of Councils, whether General, National, or Provincial; now they who deviſed and compiled this Book of Common Prayer themſelves were Proteſtants, and at the moſt and beſt but a National Council; and therefore (if true to their own faith) muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg themſelves far from being infallible in every point and thing deviſed and compiled by them; and yet for theſe mortal erring men, like unto our ſelves, to injoyn and require of all others ſuch an unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed by and in their deviſed form and ſyſtem of Worſhip, do notwithſtanding (in ſo doing in a diametrical oppoſition aſſume unto themſelves an infallible ſpirit, elſe ſtand guilty of an high preſumption in requiring ſuch a Declaration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> In the Preface to this Book of Common-Prayer they profeſs their own firm perſwaſion that there is (nor was before their laſt reviſing of it) nothing in the whole Book contrary to the Word of God or to ſound Doctrine, or which a godly man may not uſe or ſubmit unto with a good Conſcience. Now though this be their perſwaſion, yet it is not every mans perſwaſion, and therefore unreaſonable to force others to the ſame profeſſion. Haſt thou faith? have it to thy ſelf, force it not upon others; compell them not to think as thou thinkeſt, believe as thou believeſt, to declare as thou declareſt; ſtudy thine own and neighbours peace better, and the rather, becauſe thou art a fallible creature, and may be in an error as well as any other. And according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and candor of this bleſſed rule ſuch was the practice and proceedings of our preceding Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours with reference to this Book of Common-Prayer from and ſince our happy Reformation. For they never went about thus ſtrictly to injoyn the Miniſters to declare <hi>their unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by the Book,</hi> but only appoinned it to <hi>be read and uſed, and the rites and ceremonies of it duly to be obſerved,</hi> and no more. This was their moderation and piety, at leaſt their prudence and policy in reſpect of ſcandal and further incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency: and not without cauſe; for had the Miniſters in thoſe days been rigorouſly required to declare <hi>their unfeigned aſſent and conſent <add>to</add> all and every thing contained in the ſaid Book,</hi> as we <add>do</add> in our days; I am prone to believe that Hundreds of thoſe who conformed and ſubmitted to the uſe of things then eſtabliſhed in the Church, would have thereupon turned as great Non-conformiſts as any among us, and ſo continued till their laſt breath. For what a conſcientious perſon may think meet to uſe and ſubmit unto is one thing, but what he declares, he owns and approves, is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of a different nature. Though for peace ſake I could ſwallow down ſome gnats, and make no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49675:2"/>bones of them; yet if at the ſame time I ſhall moreover be compelled to ſay and avouch, That theſe gnats are no gnats; or though I know them to be gnats, yet that I like them, and love to ſwallow them down; now theſe gnats are changed into Camels, and my throat is not wide enough to give them any paſſage. Upon which very account I doubt not to declare, That preſent Conformity is foreign and quite of another nature from conformity heretofore; Conſcience being now much more forced and violated by them in the Chair. I would to God therefore they had required no more in conformity, than <hi>uſe and ſubmiſſion,</hi> as they there ſpeak; for <hi>Jobn</hi> his driving on furiouſly is dangerous, and I heartily pray the Chariot may not be overturned in the end; but in the interim I cannot keep pace with them, nor declare my unfeigned aſſent and conſent to their great zeal, nor yet to the great product and <hi>manifeſto</hi> of it in any ſuch impoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> As to a Book of Common-Prayer in general, or an eſtabliſhed Liturgy in the Church, I ſhall object nothing; for according to my poor underſtanding I never yet heard a ſound reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, why a man may not pray in a form of words preſcribed as well as from his own preſent or premeditatd conception, eſpecially where the things prayed for are not fluctuating and falling under changeable circumſtances (as the private concerns of particular perſons) but ſetled in their own nature, and always the ſame from time to time (as the publick concerns of a Nation) as the life of the King, the proſperity of the Kingdom, rain in drought, fair weather in harveſt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſee no exception why Prayers about theſe (if ſo commanded) ſhould not be made in the very ſame words; ſo likewiſe the Word and Sacraments, Baptiſm and the Lords Supper are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the ſame without any variety of intention; and therefore I judg we may always beg a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon them by a preſcribed form without any variety of expreſſion. And as I ſay nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Liturgy or preſcribed form of publick Prayers in the general, ſo neither againſt the main Doctrine contained in the the Prayers of this Book of Common Prayers in particular. But withal I look upon it as quite another thing to be bound up to declare <hi>my unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and everything contained in the Book,</hi> together with thoſe Prayers.</p>
            <p>My reaſon is this: becauſe I cannot but take <hi>aſſent and conſent,</hi> according to the general ſenſe and meaning of thoſe words among all writers and ſpeakers in all Languages, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>aſſent</hi> with reference to the party aſſenting, relates to his underſtanding and with reference to the thing aſſented to, that it relates to the truth and rightfulneſs of it. So again, that <hi>conſent</hi> with reference to the party conſenting, relates to his will; and with reference to the thing conſented to, that it relates to the goodneſs, expediency and behoofulneſs of it. Wherefore (according to the natural and genuine interpretation of theſe words <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi>) when I declare <hi>my unfeigned aſſent</hi> to all and every thing contain'd and preſcribed in and by the Book, it is all one as if I had declared, <hi>That I own and acknowledg, profeſs and witneſs, that all and every thing contained in and preſcribed by the Book of Common Prayer is true and right, and not the leaſt error in it from top to bottom, not in any rite or cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, not in the form and manner of making, ordaining, and conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts or Deacons, no not ſo much as in pointing the Pſalms,</hi> or in any other tittle or circumſtance: So again, when I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <hi>my unfeigned conſent</hi> to all and every thing contained in it, it is all one as if I had declared, <hi>That I heartily and cordially cloſe in and chuſe every thing mentioned and preſcribed in the ſaid Book as good and expedient, as most eligible and behooful to be done, practiſed, and obſerved</hi> Now that this is the true meaning of the word <hi>conſent,</hi> the Law-givers themſelves (who beſt underſtood their own mind and intention) make it moſt evident; for in the very body of the ſame Act ſpeaking of Lectures, <hi>viz.</hi> what theſe are to do and declare, inſtead of the word <hi>conſent</hi> they put in the word <hi>approve,</hi> as a word <hi>equipollent,</hi> and of the ſame ſignification; For the Lecturer is bound openly and publickly to declare <hi>his aſſent to and approbation of the ſaid Book, and to the uſe of all the Prayers, Rites, Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, forms and orders therein contained and preſcribed.</hi> Now taking theſe words <hi>aſſent and conſent</hi> this ſenſe and meaning (and otherwiſe I cannot take them to make any found ſenſe of them) I dare as ſoon eat hot fire-coals as declare my <hi>unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in and by the Book of Common-Prayer;</hi> becauſe ſeveral things are therein contained and preſcribed, which I deem ſcarce right and true, much leſs good and expedient to be done and embraced. And here to omit many things which I ſcruple, I ſhall pitch only upon two or three, which I cannot approve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I neither do nor can approve of the Order appointed for the reading of the holy Scripture; my reaſon is this, Becauſe many Books of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> are commanded to be read for the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the day, as the fabulous Legends of <hi>Tobit</hi> and his Dog, <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon, Judith</hi> &amp; <hi>Baruch,</hi> with the reſt; and theſe are not only to be read wholly &amp; intirely morning and evening two months together, but all of them alſo under the title and notion of holy Scripture; for ſo in the whole lump together they are ſtiled in the order, and no note of diſcrimination to make any diſtinction between one and other. But now in the interim, in the ſaid order (as appears by the Kalender) ſome Books of the Sacred Canon are wholly left out and never to be read; ſome of them within a very little; ſome of them but half to be read, and many of them mutilated and curtail'd as to ſeveral Chapters contained in them. Here I cannot declare my unfeigned aſſent and conſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I neither do nor can approve of the order appointed for the Miniſtration of Baptiſm. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of God-fathers and God-mothers. 2. Becauſe of the Croſs. 3. Becauſe of what is annexed at the end of the Sacrament. I do not approve of the ſtrict requiring of God-fathers and God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ſtand as Sureties and undertakers for the Child to be baptized, <hi>viz. That he ſhall renounce the Devil and all his works, and conſtantly believe Gods holy word, and obediently keep his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> 1. Becauſe it is unſcriptural. 2. Becauſe in the interim the father of the child is left out,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49675:2"/>if not wholly thruſt out, I am ſure he is not mentioned nor taken notice of at all in that publick ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation, as if he had no concern in it; though it muſt needs be his proper and peculiar Province and place to undertake ſuch a charge for his own child and fleſh, according to the Law of God and nature. Scripture requires not God-fathers but fathers to bring up their children in the <hi>nurture and admonition of the Lord.</hi> 3. Becauſe God-fathers and God mothers are generally brought to the Font to avouch a great untruth, and make themſelves obnoxious of lying and perjury in the face of God and the Church. For experience ſheweth, that though they ſolemnly engage in ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, yet they never (or very rarely) perform it; perhaps ſome of them never ſee the child more after the Chriſtning day, nor ever enquire more about it. Yea though they ſo ſolemnly engage on the behalf of the Infant, yet they hold themſelvs never the more engaged, but look upon all as a meer Chriſtning Ceremony and complement. For ſuppoſe a Parent afterward ſhould challenge his Goſſips and ſay, you promiſed when you ſtood Sureties for my child at the Font, to call upon him to hear Sermons, and to ſee him well inſtructed in the rudiments and principles of Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but you have not done it; and through your neglect he does not hear Sermons, he is not Catechiſed, he does not renounce the works of the Devil, but is in the high way to ruin, notwithſtanding your engagements: What now would be the anſwer of theſe perſons to the Parents of the Child? Should we look after him or you? whoſe child is he, yours or ours? He is your own proper charge not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our ſtanding at the Font; he is a Talent committed to your truſt, and therefore if he do otherwiſe than well for lack of your care, the blame will be yours, and his blood will be upon your head, as the only criminal. Indeed none in my obſervation blame the God-fathers and God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers if Children be not well diſciplin'd and educated, neither do they blame themſelves, nor ſhew any conſcience in this matter; though yet it is evident againſt them, that if Covenants be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by them to the utmoſt of their power, they have broken their faith. Therefore upon the whole matter I judg it far better that ſuch perſons ſhould not be called to be Sureties, nor ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes required at their hands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, I cannot approve of the Croſs in Baptiſm, eſpecially the Sacramental and myſtical way and manner of ſigning with this ſign, as thus, <hi>We receive this Child into the congregation of Chriſts flock, and do ſign him with the ſign of the Croſs in token hereafter he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs the faith of Chriſt crucified, and manfully fight under Chriſts banner, againſt Sin, the World and the Devil, &amp;c.</hi> This word, <hi>in token,</hi> I confeſs to me is a meer riddle, and I know not what to make of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot <hi>aſſent and conſent</hi> to ſuch an expreſſion; and the rather becauſe I am apt to believe the generality may much miſtake it, as if when it is ſaid, <hi>in token,</hi> it had been ſaid, <hi>in vertue and power of this ſign</hi> the perſon baptized ſhould not be aſhamed to confeſs the Faith of Chriſt crucified, but ſhould fight manfully under Chriſts banner againſt Sin, the World, and the Devil; ſurely even ſuch an occaſion of a miſunderſtanding to the vulgar and injudicious, ſhould be taken away.</p>
            <p>The baptizing it ſelf of any perſon in the name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> does oblige the perſon baptized to confeſs the Faith of Chriſt crucified, and withal exhibits a virtue and power alſo to every worthy partaker of it to fight againſt Sin, the World and the Devil; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore after ſuch a perſon is baptized, ſuch an obligation is upon him, and ſuch a vertue and power ſuppoſed to be imparted and communicated unto him; and conſequently (if at all) next immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after waſhing or ſprinkling in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, that form of words, <hi>In token hereafter he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs the Faith of Chriſt crucified, &amp;c.</hi> would more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and congruouſly be uſed and applied. But now to remove them from their due place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them to the ſign of the Croſs, as if baptizing with water were not ſuſſicient of it ſelf, but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the ſign of the Croſs needful to bind the Conſcience, and confer the bleſſing, this I confeſs ſeems to me not only prepoſterous but very dangerous. Croſſing in this manner is too too like a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon a Sacrament, the deviſed Sacrament of man to the inſtituted Sacrament of God.</p>
            <p>Though Chriſtians in the Primitive times might make uſe of the ſign of the Croſs, yet the very ſame reaſon which might put them upon that uſe with a reference to the Heathens, ſhould now move us wholly to diſuſe it with a reference to <hi>Papiſts;</hi> Profeſſors then ſigned themſelves with the ſign of the Croſs to diſtinguiſh themſelves from the Pagans, who ſcorned the Croſs together with every ſign and token of it; and with parity of reaſon we ſhould now forbear ſo doing to diſtinguiſh our ſelves from the Idolatrous <hi>Papiſts;</hi> who ſuperſtitiouſly adore the Croſs, fooliſhly, fondly, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſigning themſelves with it upon every occaſion, thinking themſelves no good Catholicks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo doing, putting no little hope and confidence in it to free and protect them from all evil, and to furniſh and inveſt them with all good. Now to witneſs our diſlike and deteſtation of their vanity herein, I cannot unfeignedly aſſent and conſent to the ſign of the Croſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I cannot approve what is annexed in the end of the Sacrament, <hi>viz. It is certain by Gods word, that children which are baptized dying before they commit actual ſin are undoubtedly ſaved.</hi> I would they had quoted the place, for I confeſs mine own ignorance that I know no ſuch word in Scripture; no ſuch word as will give me a certainty of perſwaſion beyond all poſſibility of doubting of the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Infants, though baptized, and though dying before they have committed actual ſin.</p>
            <p>Are not the Children of wicked Parents (filthy Whoremongers and Whores living openly in all notorious ſin, and wholly without God in the world) conſtantly baptized? and many of them dying immediately after Baptiſim? Now are we ſure by the Word of God, and without doubt that all theſe go to Heaven? Methinks that in the ſecond Commandment gives ſome ſcruple to my faith, <hi>I will puniſh the iniquity of the fathers upon their children to the third and fourth generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Chriſtian King ſhould conquer a Country of Pagans, and <hi>Mahometans,</hi> or <hi>Jews,</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49675:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>compel all their Infants forthwith to be baptized, and ſome of them immediately expire, at leaſt before they have committed actual ſin; is the Salvation of all ſuch ſure and paſt all doubt, and this to be made out, and cleared by the Word of God?</p>
            <p>Is it in the power of man to make Infants ſure and certain of Salvation? It is in the power of man to kill a poor Infant, and to chuſe his time for doing of it; I am ſure many Whores murder their Babes before Baptiſm, and they may as well do it after, immediately after, and ſo aſſuredly ſend their Infants thither, whither they ſhall never come themſelves except they repent. And ſo might the foreſaid King and Conqueror (after by Baptiſm he had given them their ſure and unqueſtionable paſport for Paradice) he might even in charity and kindneſs immediately cut them off, and without any further hazzard give them poſſeſſion of eternal bliſs. I had thought no mortal wight had had ſuch power over ſouls.</p>
            <p>May a Miniſter, ſince Baptizing gives ſuch an unqueſtionable title unto Heaven, deny or ſuſpend the Ordinance to any Infant whatſoever, if he might be permitted to adminiſter it? Suppoſe <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould quietly permit him to baptize their Children, yea and deſire him to do it for them, though meerly upon ſome by-pretence and foreign to Chriſtianity; ſhall he deny them? But ſuppoſe a true Believer and a good Chriſtian ſhould bring his own Child to the Font, and beg there of the Miniſter to have it baptized, but yet either <hi>out of weakneſs or tenderneſs of conſcience ſcruples God-fathers and God-mothers, and the ſign of the Croſs, and dares not admit of them;</hi> ſhall therefore the Miniſter deny his Babe Chriſtendom, which according to his own perſwaſion would give the Babe a certain aſſurance of Salvation? and keep it in the interim under a ſuſpicion of damnation, and this alſo according to his own perſwaſion? for as he denies it Chriſtendom, ſo alſo he would deny it Chriſtian burial, if it die unbaptized; (though by the way I ſee no great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, nor can I approve of it) but ſo it is appointed, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Office of the Dead ſhall nor be uſed for any who die unbaptized:</hi> And why not uſed? Becauſe they have no ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hope of a Reſurrection unto life concerning ſuch a perſon, and therefore the unbaptized in that Order are ranked with ſelf-murderers and excommunicate. But now ſhall a Miniſter dare to with-hold ſo much good from, and endeavour ſo much evil to the ſouls of poor Infants in denying them their Chriſtendom, and all meerly upon the account of ſome acceſſories and ſcrupled acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents invented and impoſed by man, and nothing at all of the eſſence of Baptiſin it ſelf? Beſides the impiety and irreligion of ſuch a Proceſs, the Miniſter (according to his own faith) would be moſt cruel and unmerciful in ſo doing, and deſerved if poſſible to be unchriſtened himſelf again, and turn'd among <hi>Canibals</hi> as one more deeply dipt and baptized in their barbarous inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity than any of themſelves; and <hi>yet if he be a true Son of the Church, and punctually obſerve his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed rule, he muſt not baptize any Infant without God-fathers and God-mothers without ſigning of it with the ſign of the Croſs, whether it be ſaved or damned.</hi> But theſe things are hard to aſſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto, and I cannot do it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I cannot approve of the order for the burial of the Dead particularly that paſſage of it, <hi>Foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed God of his great mercy to take unto himſelf the ſoul of our dear Brother here departed, we therefore commit his body to the ground, &amp;c.</hi> My reaſon is this, Becauſe though we be bound to judg according to the utmoſt Bounds of charity concerning all, yea even of thoſe with whom we would not change ſouls, nor be in their condition after death for ten thouſand worlds, yet poſitively and peremptorily without all limitation or diſcrimination to ſay and avouch concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one whom we bury, <hi>That God in great mercy has taken his ſoul,</hi> viz. <hi>by death out of the body, and taken it to himſelf;</hi> this I profeſs is utterly beyond my faith, and of the Goſpel alſo; which (if I underſtand aright) ſpeaks altogether in another language to impenitent ſinners. It is paſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction that thouſands are cut off by God in the midſt of their ſins, drunkenneſs, whoring, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without all ſigns of repentance from firſt to laſt, ſo living and ſo dying; now how can it be ſaid, <hi>That God took away ſuch perſons out of this world by death in mercy, in great mercy?</hi> Inaſmuch as at the ſame inſtant they were taken away from all poſſibility of future repentance and amendment of life, we may rather fear, <hi>That God took them away in wrath, in great wrath,</hi> provoked hereunto by the long abuſe of his patience, and their own impenitency. Yet nevertheleſs the Prieſt muſt not only ſay, That God took away all ſuch perſons <hi>in mercy, in great mercy,</hi> but moreover poſitively affirm, <hi>That God took them to himſelf;</hi> that is, into Heaven, if we believe the Lords-Prayer, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> there God is ſaid to be in a moſt eminent manner. Scripture ſaith expreſly, That neither Adulterers, nor Fornicators, nor Drunkards, ſhall ever go to Heaven, yet in a perfect oppoſition, when I bury a known Adulterer, Fornicator, Drunkard, I muſt declare and avouch that <hi>his ſoul is aſſuredly gone thither.</hi> I dare not thus damn a perſon while he is living, and yet ſave him when he is dead. Nor yet again can I <hi>commit his body to the ground in a ſure and certain hope of a Reſurrection unto eternal life;</hi> which words muſt neceſſarily be ſpoken with reference to the perſon then interred, inaſmuch as they are the continuation of the foregoing declaration, <hi>viz. God's taking his ſoul to himſelf.</hi> Beſides it follows (which puts it out of doubt) in the laſt Collect or Prayer, <hi>That when we ſhall depart this life, we may reſt in him</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt) <hi>as our hope is this our Brother doth.</hi> Alas, I am ſo far from having <hi>any ſure and certain hope of his Reſurrection unto eternal life and ſalvation,</hi> that I rather <hi>have a ſure and certain fear of his Reſurrection unto eternal death and damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> Theſe are ſome of my Objections againſt the firſt Declaration, which ſtop up my way from conforming.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>A. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
